[Music]
welcome back to the real news network uh
reality asserts itself and I'm with John
Kaku and he and I were started arguing
as we uh were waiting for the cameras to
go back on I said wait a sec let's turn
them on and let's argue for real in
front of the cameras and what we're
arguing about is I'm saying I think
there's evidence I can't say it's proven
or definitive but I think in a normal
court of law you could get somebody
charged with the amount of evidence
there is at least you could get an
indictment whether you get a conviction
or not I don't know that someone very
senior in the White House and from what
we know the someone is likely to be uh
vice president Richard Cheney and please
Mr Cheney please sue me for liable I
would love to have this out in court uh
so please if if if by any chance you're
watching um there's there is evidence
that the intelligence agent gencies in
the United States were more or less told
to stand down when it comes to fighting
terrorism Richard Clark is demoted
George Tennant tells the White House in
a presidential uh his first Bush's first
presidential briefing Bin Laden and uh
Al-Qaeda is the number one threat to uh
National Security and in fact what
happens is this terrorism and the secur
that security threat is demoted FBI is
told not to prioritize
terrorism John told us in the summer
that the head of the counter terrorism
unit the CIA told him that they were
expecting something massive coming
cannot get cond Lisa Rice to listen um
so I'm saying this ain't just not
listening and it isn't just an
intelligence failure and John says hi
John go ahead I'm no fan of Dick Cheney
I never was I think he's a Malignant
Force in the history of our country but
I just can't believe that someone who is
charged with running our country would
be so
Psychopathic as to encourage a massive
attack I mean I it just doesn't make any
kind of logical sense to me I can tell
you that at the CIA we were never told
to stand down while we certainly needed
uh a greater counterterrorism budget we
were doing everything humanly possible
to try to infiltrate al-Qaeda in 2001
and to try to disrupt this attack that
we knew was coming but you had good
information we had some information
we're getting it in bits and pieces and
the analysts put it together and and
decided that that uh Ben Laden was
determined to attack the United States
don't you think you had enough to tell
immigration to be extra strict don't you
think he had enough to maybe take a a
closer look at Saudi immigration don't
you think that the Federal Aviation
Authority should have been sure but
you're talking about the security threat
level you're talking about policy
changes and you know it's a fact of life
in the United States we're a big
lumbering bureaucracy and policy changes
can take months or years but this goes
back to this belief of yours that you
cannot believe that a leader of the
United States would allow something like
this to happen but I also don't think
that he had the power to do something
like that the the the bureaucracy is
just simply too vast and and Cheney was
powerful but he wasn't powerful enough
to
single-handedly stop the wheels of the
intelligence community and allow uh
Al-Qaeda into the country to launch an
attack then you give me another
explanation how condalisa rice doesn't
listen when the CIA says something
massive is coming maybe condalisa rice
was an incompetent boob I mean there's
that school of thought
too because you can't believe it all
goes to a question of Faith underlying
sure I ad if you were a cop looking at a
murderer and you just had this as
straightforward evidence or an CIA
analyst if it wasn't a leader of the
United States I can't believe you would
you just can't the most likely what I'm
suggesting there's evidence of is not a
massive conspiracy I agree with you I
think a massive conspiracy is impossible
to keep covered uh I'm suggesting that
someone very senior like VI president
Cheney understands the way the American
bureaucracy works and he knows if you
deprioritize if you don't take any extra
measures to make sure the agencies are
talking to each other like let's go
another way which it could have done mhm
Osama Bin Laden plans to attack United
States uhoh let's get all the heads of
agencies that might have anything to do
with us in a meeting and say Jesus are
we prepared just in case something is
coming here uh oh CIA is saying
something massive is coming and put that
together what the CIA just told us that
it might be in the United States Ki
don't you think you better get Clark and
get tenant in here and get the FBI and
maybe who else you need and and make
sure you guys are actually talking to
each other about stuff I mean if you
were running a hamburger stand that's
what you would do that's what you would
do yes I agree and Cheney ain't
stupid you know George ain't stupid but
he's not as bright as Cheney
is not to do that suggests perhaps it's
a decision not to do that I I'll agree
with you with you that it's certainly
worth investigating and there wasn't an
adequate and appropriate
investigation let's go back a step let's
let go back and Stu you know the story
how Richard
Nixon sabotaged Lyndon Johnson's peace
talks with the northes sure because of
Nixon perhaps hundreds of thousands of
Vietnamese and cambodians died because
of he sabotaged those talks now maybe
they would have fallen apart anyway
maybe but we do know and we have it from
the Johnson Library the actual audio
tape where lynon Johnson says Nixon is
acting like a traitor some of our folks
including ining some of the old China
Lobby are going to the Vietnamese
Embassy and saying please notify the
president that if he'll hold out till
November the 2nd they could get a better
deal uhhuh now I'm reading their hand
ever I don't want to get this in the
campaign that's right and they ought to
be doing this this is treason now
there's the president of the United
States I mean about to be president of
the United States acting like a traitor
sabotaging What Might Have Been a peace
agreement for his own agenda so how's
that any different than what I'm
suggesting so here's a leader of the
United States that was willing to do
that but I'm not sure he was willing to
do that I'm again I'm not defending Dick
Cheney I'm just not ascribing to him
these Supernatural powers to to allow a
terrorist group into the United States
nothing Supernatural just demote Richard
Clark tell r that was a political
decision to demote Richard Clark maybe
then as we said then get rid of Richard
Clark If you don't like Richard Clark
fireman replace him with someone you
like don't demote the office it was my
understanding that Richard Clark asked
to stay on the National Security Council
and they created the cyber security Zar
position for him later immediately he
moved directly from one job into the
other he moved directly from
counterterrorism into cyber security but
when his hair is on fire and cond Lisa
Rice won't listen to their CIA when they
say something massive is coming their
counter terrorism are something's
massive is coming this can't just be
competence at least it should be
investigated I know you're going to get
that I agree with I agree it should be
investig this is your underlying faith
that that a leader of the United States
would never do such a thing to his own
country Americans no I don't think so I
I just I I can't believe it it's too
much all right let's move on okay um
where are you on 9911 I was in CIA
headquarters on 911 I was supposed to go
downtown with uh kofer black to see
condalisa rice uh on issue related to
Greek terrorism and um I I had gotten a
call that our car was ready uh to to
take us downtown so I walked over to
cofer's office and just outside his
office his secretary was sitting and she
was watching TV and one of the towers of
the World Trade Center was burning and I
said uh what happened to the World Trade
Center and she said a a plane flew into
it and me not really giving it much
thought
said or I should I should say I not
giving it much thought said you know
that happened in the 1930s a plane flew
into the Empire State Building but it
was really foggy then and it's so clear
today how can you not see that you're
flying into the World Trade Center and
as I said that the second plane flew
into uh Tower
1 and neither one of us reacted and
finally she turned to me she was sitting
down I was standing behind her and she
said did you see that it was as though
our brains couldn't even register what
we had just seen so I ran back to my
office and I told my colleagues guys I
think we're under attack two planes just
hit both towers of the World Trade
Center we turned on the TV and then the
Pentagon was hit so everybody gathered
in this huge office that is the cia's
counterterrorism
center uh there were TVs mounted uh from
the ceiling hanging down on PO like in
24 the TV show kind of a room like that
kind kind of yeah great big open we
called it a cubicle Farm must had 300
cubicles in it so we're all gathered
around watching The Towers burn watching
the Pentagon burn and then finally
somebody in the back of the crowd shouts
will somebody please
lead and that was like it was as though
somebody had shaken cover and he snapped
out of it and started barking orders you
go to the director's office you go to
security you go here you go there and
then he says everybody else evacuate
and we just stood there and I heard a
couple people say I'm not going anywhere
this is what we've been working for all
this time and so it wasn't until
individual CIA policemen came to the
office and said everybody evacuate
evacuate or we're going to Cuff you and
walk you to your cars we all
evacuated so I drove to I I was driving
back to my apartment and the way I got
there was on uh the George Washington
Parkway from the CIA parking lot just
straight down toward
Washington and traffic was so bad I just
abandoned my car I walked the rest of
the way I actually saw a couple of
people that I knew uh one was a former
CIA officer who were working at the
White House at the National Security
Council and they had even abandoned the
White House and they were walking back
to their own houses and apartments so I
met my
then girlfriend now wife uh at my
apartment uh we went up to the roof and
watched the Pentagon burn for a little
while and then we went out and tried to
donate blood but the lines were so long
that it was just impossible to donate
blood and I said to her this is
ridiculous we need to go back to work
she was a CIA officer too so we walked
back to my car on the GW Parkway got in
the car went back to headquarters and
then I didn't leave for 4 days just
slept under my desk I would ball up my
jacket use that as a pillow um a couple
of officers uh took some bolt cutters
and and cut the chain off the uh the
doors to the cafeteria we went in and
stole all the food we cooked it
ourselves and just put it on on folding
tables out in the hallway so people who
were working 24 hours would have
something to eat I think we ended up
writing a check to the Marriott for like
10 or1 15,000 to replace all the food
that we took uh but nobody left
everybody stayed so when when you say
the CIA was working as hard as it could
just to prevent it I'm also sure the CIA
was working as hard as it could to find
capture or kill Bin Laden I see no
reason to think they weren't trying they
were
um but there was a great debate at the
time not in mainstream news because you
couldn't get get heard on mainstream
news but amongst people who were from
the region as well as people here that
were critics of going to massive war in
Afghanistan to start with that this
could have been more of a Black Ops
operation there could have been a real
laser focus on finding and dealing with
Al-Qaeda and Bin Laden there didn't need
to be regime change and allout war in
Afghanistan um were you aware of that
debate or argument and and why why even
in retrospect why wasn't the strategy
that in in retrospect it's my
understanding that for example the Navy
Seals of 2015 are absolutely nothing
like Navy Seals of 2001 it it's my
understanding that that we just didn't
have the the wherewithal in 2001 to be
able to not just locate uh Bin Laden I
mean we we essentially knew he was
somewhere in the torab Bora area uh he
was probably in that camp but we weren't
certain um not just that but then to
physically go in and get him I'm just
not sure that we could have done
something like that in 2001 I'm not a
military analyst so what were you
focused on in those two three weeks
after 911 what was your assignment it
was mostly name traces you know around
the world in every every American
Embassy around the world people began
walking in and saying I have information
on Al-Qaeda and they would give us these
names well there were tens of thousands
of names sometimes thousands coming in
every day and we needed an army of
Clerks is what it amounted to to uh
search all of our data bases looking in
at information uh pertaining to these
names I I was in Kandahar in the spring
of 2002 making a film called return to
Kandahar and told by numerous people and
I what I'm about to say I have no idea
what the meaning of it is I can't draw
any conclusion from it but numerous
people in cahart told me that about
something in a week and a half seven
eight nine days after 9911 Mula Omar and
Bin Laden and everybody knows where they
live which is this is another thing
which makes no sense to me everybody
knew where Bin Laden's compound was he
had you know there's like 30 20 30 white
SUVs coming in and out all day long uh
that they leave in the middle of daytime
Omar's big trail of white SUVs Bin
Laden's trail of white SUVs and they
drive to toror MH and nothing happens
but I'm not trying to suggest I know
what that means we we didn't have armed
drones at the time um and we didn't have
I mean you the the intelligence has to
be so immediate which really almost
never happens in the intelligence World
it has to be so immediate and you have
to have planes in the sky ready to
receive the the intelligence to be able
to act that quickly and S days later you
you don't have somebody on the ground in
can no how do you get into Kandahar I
mean you have to have a sponsor
somebody's got to be there to protect
you and to give you cover you can't just
you know go rent a hotel room and start
looking for bin Laden is I watch TV
somebody you go get a woman gets in a
burka and she can walk anywhere she
wants no and there's no such thing as a
live satellite feed either you see that
in TV all the time where people are
saying I need a I need a live satellite
feed now and then they watch the guy
walk through the streets of a city that
just there's no such thing then or now
even now there's no such thing but now
it'd be drones now it would be drones
you're saying there's no on a satellite
that watches everything yes well that's
good to know I
suppose um all right so you're you're
doing this name search and um what do
you make of the strategy in Afghanistan
you this I mean it was it was a very
strange moment once the allout attack
starts on the Taliban they're bombing
the hell out of cabul they run out of
things to bomb and they keep bombing
because they have to prove they're doing
something I guess I don't they think
American public opinion demands Revenge
I don't know what it is but the Northern
Alliance all the old Warlords that
actually made such a mess in Afghanistan
that it helped create the conditions for
the rise of the Taliban in the first
place they may have killed some people
think as many as 2 million people right
in the Civil War MH between who's going
to who's going to be the and one of them
is the vice president of Afghanistan
yeah we'll get to that D them uh and
then then they decide you know okay then
they being the White House the Pentagon
they decide okay we're going to make the
deal with the Warlords and they you know
shovel millions and millions of dollars
into the pockets of these War
essentially war criminals and that's and
that's the strategy for Afghanistan yeah
I think you have some of the timing
wrong though uh first Gary shron who was
a very senior Cia officer legendary
officer uh wrote a book called First in
and it's about how he and a and a small
team of of CIA Special Operations
officers were the first CIA group in
Afghanistan and they went on some like
September 12th so they were they were in
the north with u His Name Escapes Me Now
the one that was killed in the bombing
the day before September 11 with mud's
people uh later on with Do's people but
there there was a CIA presence in
Afghanistan from the days immediately
following the the uh attacks the
September 11th attacks uh there's an old
saying about Afghan Warlords that you
can't buy an Afghan warlord but you can
certainly rent one and that's the CIA
way the CIA way is to throw massive
amounts of money uh at a problem and
hope that some of it sticks and some of
it stuck now was it a success uh
probably not in the long run but at
least it bought us some time uh when I
say that it wasn't a success what I mean
is instead of these Warlords capturing
uh senior Al-Qaeda leaders and turning
them over to us we ended up filling
guantan Mo and other places with you
know largely innocent nobodies who had
been turned in uh by their neighbors for
a bounty uh or who wanted to settle
scores with people they didn't like uh
but it it did buy us some time it put
the Taliban On The Run remember we
didn't start bombing Afghanistan for
almost a month uh we we wanted to um
give mul Omar a chance to turn Bin Laden
over to us and I really believe that if
he had done that uh Al-Qaeda would have
imploded as an
organization and we would never have had
any reason to go to war in Afghanistan
and there's pretty good evidence that
and I I told you off camera I'll tell
the story again quickly I interviewed a
former member of the Taliban Central
council at hammed Kai's brother Wally
carai who himself was assassinated just
a few years ago um in in his living room
we're all on carpets in the living room
and he says that there was a there was a
a meeting of the Taliban Central Council
called by Mula Omar to debate whether or
not to hand over Bin Laden and they vote
that they will hand over Bin
Laden another meeting is called three
days later and according to this guy he
says it's the the Pakistani foreign
minister that's how it was translated
and we have all this on tape uh came to
the meeting and talked them out of
handing over Bin Laden
um the
the there's still the grounds and I go
back back to my my original question
there's still a place there where the
strategy could have been focus on
Al-Qaeda Bin Laden even mulah Omar if
you have evidence he was connected to it
and there I think there seems to be
there seems some it doesn't necessarily
call for an allout war in Afghanistan
and regime change oh I think you're
probably right first I I think that the
story is probably correct I I can't
imagine what benefit the the Taliban
Central Council
could possibly have
thought there would be to allowing Bin
Laden to remain in in Afghanistan that
just doesn't make any any sense and from
all indications mul Omar although
uneducated is very very bright and
certainly he's a great political uh
strategist at least he was um so I think
the story you heard is probably correct
uh I'm not sure that we could have
that we could have disrupted uh
destroyed
Al-Qaeda without an allout War without
the the cooperation of the Taliban I
think that we were kind of pushed into
it now was there was there a Pakistani
uh conspiracy it's very possible well
we're going to get into that quite a bit
the Pakistani side it's the only reason
I'm holding them back on that right now
okay cuz your next stop is Pakistan I'm
going to kind of wait to talk about the
Pakistani part what I'm getting at what
I think is even more important though is
the the strategy of allying with
Warlords and and essentially handing
over the poppy crops of Afghanistan as
part of the deal because that's really
what happens in Afghanistan
Afghanistan's poppy production was not
nil but next to next to n for one year
under the Taliban under the Taliban for
one year they produced 90% of the
world's uh heroin Poppy under the
Taliban it went down to zero for a year
and then back up to 90%
again I did a long in-depth study on
this when I was with the Senate Foreign
Relations Committee yeah I wouldn't
argue with Heroin poppy was was the way
the Taliban earned its money that's how
they could afford all of their Weaponry
you I can't I don't know anything to
disagree with you and I don't know why I
would uh but my point was is this gets
handed over to the Warlords oh yeah
millions and millions of dollars in
suitcases this enormous poppy crop and
then some because I think it gets far
far bigger once the Northern Alliance
warlord types take over could become we
estimated that that Afghanistan now
produces 93% of the world's heroin and
all of that heroin is produced by people
with ties to the various
Warlords
so as a strategy you're handing the
country essentially over to war
criminals and drug lords MH over here
we're hearing democracy we're invading
Afghanistan for Wom
and one I'm the only one that seems to
remember this and I don't know why cuz
nobody ever talks about this but me
President Bush went on television and
asked every child in America to donate
$1 towards children in Afghanistan it
was going to be this big program CH
children to children program last week I
asked America's
children to send a dollar to the White
House to help provide food and medicine
to the children of Afghanistan
and I'm still asking where's the money I
I'm sure some kid sent dollars in and no
one ever heard another word about this
send a dollar to save an Afghan kid geez
I hadn't heard that it was on
TV I guess I was focused on
work it it's it's a this is a strategy
which we now know was really all about
the lead up to war in Iraq that they
didn't they really didn't have much
strategy for Afghanistan other than do
something make a show of it assuming I
don't know how they assumed I guess the
Warlords will take over Afghanistan and
look after it for us and everything will
be fine the Taliban will run away and
we're going to go and and and Tiptoe
Through The daisies in Iraq I don't
disagree with that it's
insane I think that there was always a
plan to attack Iraq always from before
George W bush even won the presidency I
I think that there was a that there was
a um a movement among prominent
neoconservatives in this country to come
up with a plan so that when and if
George W bush won the presidency they
could pitch this plan to attack Iraq and
they could disguise it in any way they
wanted uh 9911 I think was the most
convenient way to do it and for them the
easiest way to
try it's it's it's it's so insane it's
so delusional like I I know like I've
interviewed Ray McGovern and some other
you know former CIA guys you guys are
sitting there trying to do real analysis
based on evidence and forign policy is
being made I I don't know what else Mr
Cheney you're a sociopath like please
suum me please I I want a chance to
prove it the foreign policy is being
made by social pest connected with what
military industrial complex a vision of
a px Americana I mean all of the above
all of the above
yes I think that's right and I always
believed too that that the animosity
between the bush White House and and
Saddam Hussein was was very personal and
that it was because of saddam's attempt
to assassinate President George HW Bush
in Kuwait in
1993 I always believed that was the
route and we have another series of
interviews we're going to be releasing
soon with a historian named Appy and he
about Vietnam and he has a very
interesting quote I may have quoted ear
earlier in our interviews here but that
Vietnam by the last year or two
completely became about proving the
strength of America oh absolutely and no
other real objectives other than
that what else was Iraq same thing it's
the same thing and look at the damage
that Iraq has done too uh it's
emboldened the Iranians uh we took out
the only uh the only thing that stood
between Iran and the rest of the Arabian
Gulf uh Saddam Hussein was the only Bull
workk against Iranian
hijman and uh we took him out for
personal reasons it made no geopolitical
sense at all and then when Dick Cheney
went on TV and tied Muhammad ATA uh to
Saddam Hussein specifically to the Iraqi
uh intelligence service station Chief in
Prague that was just a big lie out and
out lie it was was an out andout liee
there was absolutely no evidence that
Muhammad ATA ever met with any
representative of the Iraqi government
it was made up and and their rationale
of they didn't care about this buffer of
Iraq Visa Iran because this was all
about Iran anyway this was all about
regime change in Iran it was supposed to
be Iraq Syria and Iran yeah that that
Iraq was going to be the first because
in Iraq once we cross the border into
Iraq they're going to throw flowers at
us I actually heard a a senior person on
the National Security Council say that
in a video teleconference as soon as we
cross the border they're going to throw
flowers at us and I remember thinking
are these people insane but first it was
going to be Iraq and then it was going
to be Syria and then it was going to be
Iran and we were going to we were going
to kick off this Democratic human rights
loving wave across the Middle East
beginning with Iraq all formed in a sea
of blood all formed in a sea of blood
and hatched in neoconservative think
tanks in
Washington crazy stuff okay we'll pick
it up in the next segment please join us
for the continuation of reality asserts
itself with John Kaku on the Real News
[Music]
Network for